Sooyong Lee

PHD

Educational Psychology, The University of Texas at Austin

□ +1 737 865 0618 | Sooyongl09@gmail.com | 0000-0002-7964-4508 | Sooyongl/

Professional Summary _____

As a psychometrician, I specialize in applying contemporary statistical theories and techniques to my work. My research interests center around developing and utilizing statistical models, including structural equation modeling (SEM), multilevel modeling (MLM), item response theory (IRT), and mixture modeling. In my recent work, I have placed particular emphasis on Bayesian estimation as a means of modeling the relationships between variables.

Education

The University of Texas at Austin

Ph.D., Major in Quantitative Methods

Seoul, Republic of Korea

M.A., MAJOR IN EDUCATIONAL STATISTICS AND MEASUREMENT

2014-2017

Austin, Texas

2017-Present

Hanyang University

Korea University

B.A. MAJOR IN SOCIOLOGY

Seoul, Republic of Korea 2007-2014

Research experience _____

CGS PhD Career Pathways project

Graduate Research Assistant

2018/9-2019/5

• Data analysis for surveys to collect data on the career pathways of past and present STEM and humanities PhD students.

President's Award for Global Learning (PAGL)

Graduate Research Assistant

PRESIDENT'S AWARD FOR GLOBAL LEARNING (PAGL)

2019/1-2019/8

• Designing a culturally appropriate mobile application to increase mental health literacy and self-care habits among South Korean young adults

COE Full-Time Tenured and Tenure-Track Faculty

Graduate Research Assistant

2019/9-2019/12

• Data analysis for surveys of graduate programs of education at the University of Texas at Austin

MAAT package development project

Graduate Research Assistant

NORTHWEST EVALUATION ASSOCIATION (NWEA)

2019/9-2020/5

• Development of MAAT package for Computerized Adaptive Testing for Northwest Evaluation Association (NWEA)

FLPS project

Graduate Research Assistant

2021/9-Present

• Development of FLPS package for Fully-latent Principal Stratification

Embedded Standard Setting (ESS)

Intern

CREATIVE MEASUREMENT SOLUTIONS LLC

2020/6-2020/8

Internship for developing Shiny app for Embedded Standard Setting

Embedded Standard Setting (ESS)

Intern

CREATIVE MEASUREMENT SOLUTIONS LLC

2021/6-2020/8

Internship for developing ESS package for Embeded Standard Setting

Teaching experience _____

EDP 380C: Structural Equation Modeling

PROFESSOR TIFFANY WHITTAKER

Teaching Assistant 2020/1-2020/5

EDP 380C: Structural Equation Modeling

PROFESSOR TIFFANY WHITTAKER

Teaching Assistant 2021/1-2021/5

Publications

2021

Cory L. Cobb, Charles R. Martínez, Jr., **Sooyong Lee**, Tae Kyoung Lee, & Elma I. Lorenzo-Blanco (2021). Acculturation trajectories differ by youth age at arrival and time in residency among Latino immigrant families in a US emerging immigrant context. *International Journal of Intercultural Relations*. 81, 79-93. DOI:10.1016/j.ijintrel. 2021.01.005.

2022

- Seung Choi, Sangdon Lim, Luping Niu, **Sooyong Lee**, Christina M. Schneider, Jay Lee, & Garron J. (2022). maat: An R Package for Multiple Administrations Adaptive Testing. *Applied Psychological Measurement*. 46-1, 73-74. DOI:10.1177/01466216211049212.
- **Sooyong Lee** & Tiffany A. Whittaker (2022). Comparison of Three Approaches to Class Enumeration in Growth Mixture Modeling when Time Structures are Variant Across Latent Classes. *Structural Equation Modeling: A Multi-disciplinary Journal*. 29, 23-35. DOI:10.1080/10705511.2021.1956320.
- **Sooyong Lee** & Tiffany A. Whittaker (2022). Parallel Process Latent Growth Modeling with Multivariate Confounders/Suppresson Structural Equation Modeling: A Multidisciplinary Journal. DOI: 10.1080/10705511.2022.2133774.
- **Sooyong Lee**, Kahyun Lee, & Tiffany A. Whittaker (2022). Application of Associative Discrete-Time Survival Analysis Using Latent Transition Specification. *Structural Equation Modeling: A Multidisciplinary Journal*. DOI:10.1080/10705511.2022.2138892.
- **Sooyong Lee**, Suhwa Han, & Seung W. Choi (2022). DIF Detection With Zero-Inflation Under the Factor Mixture Modeling Framework. *Educational and Psychological Measurement*. 82-4, 678-704. DOI: 10.1177/00131644211028995.

2023

- **Sooyong Lee**, Adam Sales, Hyeon-Ah Kang, & Tiffany A. Whittaker (2023). Fully-Latent Principal Stratification. *The Annual Meeting of the Psychometric Society*. Conference proceedings, In print.
- **Sooyong Lee**, Adam Sales, Hyeon-Ah Kang, & Tiffany A. Whittaker (2023). Comparison between Bayesian or ML in FLPS with Small Sample Sizes. In progress.
- Sooyong Lee, Adam Sales, Hyeon-Ah Kang, & Tiffany A. Whittaker (2023). Multidimensional FLPS. In progress.
- **Sooyong Lee**, Suhwa Han, & Seung W. Choi (2023). Bayesian MIMIC for DIF Detection under Violation of Equal Variance Assumption. *Educational and Psychological Measurement*. In review.
- Tiffany A. Whittaker, Laura Stapleton & **Sooyong Lee** (2023). A Tutorial for Obtaining Item Response Theory Results from Structural Equation Modeling in Mplus Software with Rating Scales. *Structural Equation Modeling: A Multidisciplinary Journal*. In review.

Presentation

Presentation

Daniel Lewis & **Sooyong Lee** (2021-04-01). *A Comparison of Two ESS Cut Score Estimation Algorithms*. National Council on Measurement in Education (NCME), Baltimore, MD, USA.

- Garron Gianopulos, Jay Lee, Sangdon Lim, Luping Niu, **Sooyong Lee**, & Seung W. Choi (2022-04-01). *The Impact of Item Pool Size and Item Pool Distribution on Student Ability Estimates for a Hybrid Interim-Summative CAT*. National Council on Measurement in Education (NCME), San Diego, USA.
- Jay Lee, M. Christina Schneider, Garron Gia, Luping Niu, **Sooyong Lee**, Sangdon Lim, & Seung W. Choi (2022-04-01). *The Impact of item bank transition rules on student ability estimates and achievement level classifications*. National Council on Measurement in Education (NCME), San Diego, USA.
- **Sooyong Lee**, Adam Sales, Hyeon-Ah Kang, & Tiffany A. Whittaker (2022-07-01). *Fully-Latent Principal Stratilication*. International Meeting of the Psychometric Society (IMPS), Bologna, Italy.

Poster

- Kejin Lee, **Sooyong Lee**, & Youngri Lee (2018-05-01). *An Alternative Approach to Discrete-Time Survival Analysis for Meaningful Interpretation*. Modern Modeling Methods conference (MMM), Connecticut, USA.
- **Sooyong Lee** & Sehee Hong (2018-07-01). *Exploration of LCA conditions in Latent Class with Low Proportion*. International Meeting of the Psychometric Society (IMPS), New York, USA.
- **Sooyong Lee** & Tiffany A. Whittaker (2020-04-01). *Comparison of Three Approaches to Class Enumeration in Growth Mixture Modeling when Time Structures are Variant Across Latent Classes*. American Educational Research Association (AERA), Virtual.
- **Sooyong Lee** & Suhwa Han (2020-07-01). *Item selection and trait estimation methods in CAT with item leakage*. International Meeting of the Psychometric Society (IMPS), Maryland, USA.
- **Sooyong Lee**, Suhwa Han, & Seung W. Choi (2021-04-01). *DIF Detection with Zero-Inflation under the Mixture Modeling Framework*. American Educational Research Association (AERA), Virtual.

Program_

2020-21 William Hays Endowed Fellowship

2021-22 Benjamin & Dorothy Fruchter Excellence Award

<pre>GRshiny: Graded response model • https://sooyongl.github.io/GRShiny/</pre>	Shiny application 2022
<pre>Embeded Standard Setting • https://sooyonglee.shinyapps.io/ESS_test/</pre>	Shiny application 2021
<pre>Embeded Standard Setting • https://sooyongl.github.io/EmStanS/</pre>	R package 2022
<pre>maat package • https://choi-phd.github.io/maat/</pre>	R package 2022
<pre>flps package • https://sooyongl.github.io/flps/</pre>	R package 2022
<pre>clavaan package • https://github.com/sooyongl/clavaan</pre>	R package 2023
Fellowship & Awards	

Fellowship

Award